This animation shows ESA’s Planck spacecraft mapping the entire sky at microwave wavelengths.
By scanning from the second Lagrange point, Planck measured tiny temperature ripples in the cosmic microwave background.
These ripples, only tens to hundreds of microkelvin, trace density variations in the early Universe.
After component separation, foregrounds like dust and synchrotron are removed to reveal the CMB signal.
One widely used reconstruction is SMICA, a method that combines Planck’s frequency maps into a clean CMB map.
The Galactic plane is masked in some visualisations to highlight high-latitude CMB anisotropies.
The resulting all-sky map encodes the initial conditions that grew into today’s galaxies and clusters.
From this map, scientists derive angular power spectra that constrain the contents and geometry of the Universe.
Planck’s 2018 data release remains a key reference for temperature and polarization measurements of the CMB.
Learn more in the Planck Legacy Archive and ESA resources linked on this page.